Edwin J. Feulner Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Edwin J. Feulner Papers 1934-2014 1966-2012
MSS85758
Feulner, Edwin J.
380,000 items
889 containers plus 8 oversize
357 linear feet
108 digital files (17.6 GB)
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Author, political consultant, former president of the Heritage Foundation. Correspondence, diaries, appointment books, daily schedules, notebooks, clippings, chronological files, biographical material, family papers, speech and travel files, itineraries, meeting files, financial records, legal records, memoranda, organization files, meeting minutes, reports, subject files, memorabilia, photographs, writings, notes, and other papers relating to Feulner's career devoted to conservative public policy and the rise of the Heritage Foundation as the leading conservative think tank and public policy research organization during Feulner's presidency.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Allen, Richard V.--Correspondence.; Bell, Belden--Correspondence.; Bennett, William J. (William John), 1943- --Correspondence.; Brown, David R. (Orthopedic surgeon)--Correspondence.; Buckley, William F., Jr., 1925-2008--Correspondence.; Bush, George, 1924-2018--Correspondence.; Coors, Joseph, 1917-2003--Correspondence.; Crane, Philip M., 1930-2014--Correspondence.; Crane, Philip M., 1930-2014.; Davis, Shelby Cullom, 1909-1994--Correspondence.; Decter, Midge--Correspondence.; Feulner, Edwin J.; Feulner, Edwin J. the Republican Study Committee, 1970-1982. Conservatives stalk the House: 1983.; Friedman, Milton, 1912-2006--Correspondence.; Gingrich, Newt--Correspondence.; Hayek, Friedrich A. von (Friedrich August), 1899-1992--Correspondence.; Kemp, Jack, 1935-2009--Correspondence.; Kemp, Jack, 1935-2009.; Kirk, Russell--Correspondence.; Krieble, Robert Henry, 1916-1997--Correspondence.; Laird, Melvin R.; Lefever, Ernest W.--Correspondence.; Lehrman, Lewis E.--Correspondence.; Lipsett, Donald J. (Donald Jerome), 1930-1995--Correspondence.; Luce, Clare Boothe, 1903-1987--Correspondence.; Meese, Edwin--Correspondence.; Middendorf, John William, 1924- --Correspondence.; Reagan, Ronald--Correspondence.; Reagan, Ronald.; Regnery, Henry, 1912-1996--Correspondence.; Rench, J. Frederic--Correspondence.; Roe, Thomas Anderson--Correspondence.; Rumsfeld, Donald, 1932-2021--Correspondence.; Saunders, Thomas A., III, 1937- --Correspondence.; Scaife, Richard M., 1932-2014--Correspondence.; Shakespeare, Frank J. (Frank Joseph), 1925- --Correspondence.; Simon, William E., 1927-2000--Correspondence.; Thatcher, Margaret--Correspondence.; Weyrich, Paul M.--Correspondence.
Organizations
Aequus Institute.; Alpha Kappa Psi.; Clare Boothe Luce Program.; Council for National Policy (U.S.); Credit International Bank (Washington, D.C.); George Mason University.; Georgetown University. Center for Strategic Studies.; Henry Luce Foundation.; Heritage Foundation (Washington, D.C.); House Republican Conference (U.S.); Institute for European Defence & Strategic Studies.; Intercollegiate Studies Institute.; National Commission on Economic Growth and Tax Reform (U.S.); Philadelphia Society.; Regis University (Denver, Colo.); Republican Study Committee (U.S.); Republican Task Force on East-West Trade.; Sarah Scaife Foundation.; Schuchman Foundation Center for the Public Interest.; Sequoia National Bank (Md.); United Nations.; United States Advisory Commission on Public Diplomacy.; United States. Congress.; United States. Congress. House.
Subjects
Commercial policy.; Conservatism--United States.; Economic policy.; Finance, Public--United States.; Free enterprise--United States.; Free trade--United States.; International economic relations.; International relations.; International trade.; Military policy.; Military readiness.; National security--United States.; Policy sciences--Research--United States.; Policy sciences--United States.; Presidents--United States--Election--1980.; Presidents--United States--Election--1996.; Public policy.; Public welfare--United States.; Research institutes--United States.; Social policy.; Social service--United States.; Social values--United States.; Taxation--United States.; Values--United States.; Vice-Presidents--United States--Election--1996.
Places
China--Foreign relations--United States.; Hong Kong (China)--Foreign relations--United States.; Japan--Foreign relations--United States.; South Korea--Foreign relations--United States.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--United States.; Taiwan--Foreign relations--United States.; Thailand--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Defenses.; United States--Economic policy--20th century.; United States--Economic policy--21st century.; United States--Foreign relations--1945-1989.; United States--Foreign relations--1989-; United States--Foreign relations--China--Hong Kong.; United States--Foreign relations--China.; United States--Foreign relations--Japan.; United States--Foreign relations--South Korea.; United States--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; United States--Foreign relations--Taiwan.; United States--Foreign relations--Thailand.; United States--Military policy--20th century.; United States--Military policy--21st century.; United States--Moral conditions--20th century.; United States--Moral conditions--21st century.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.; United States--Politics and government--21st century.; United States--Social conditions--1945-; United States--Social policy--20th century.; United States--Social policy--21st century.
Occupations
Authors.; Political consultants.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Edwin J. Feulner, author, political consultant, and former president of the Heritage Foundation, were given to the Library of Congress in 2012. Further additions were given by him in 2013 and 2015.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Audiotapes and videotapes have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Edwin J. Feulner Papers.
Access and Restrictions
Restrictions apply governing the use, photoduplication, or publication of items in this collection. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for information concerning these restrictions. In addition, many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Digital Format
Digital files were received as part of the papers of Edwin J. Feulner. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for more information
Biographical Note
Date Event
1941, Aug. 12 Born, Chicago, Ill.
1963 B.S. in English literature and business administration, Regis University, Denver, Colo.
1964 M.B.A., Wharton School of Commerce and Finance, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pa.
1964 Co-founder and member, Philadelphia Society; president, 1982-1983, 2013-2014
1965 Awarded Richard M. Weaver Fellowship by Intercollegiate Society of Individualists (later Intercollegiate Studies Institute) to attend the London School of Economics and Political Science, London, England
1965 1968 Pursued graduate studies in economics, Georgetown University, Washington, D.C.
1966 Public Affairs Fellow, Center for Strategic Studies, Washington, D.C., researching and writing about trade policy with the Soviet Union; fellowship transferred to Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace, 1967
1967 1968 Public Affairs Fellow, Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace, Stanford University, Stanford, Calif., working on staff of United States Representative Melvin R. Laird, and further delegated to staff of Republican Task Force on East-West Trade
1968 Published with Samuel F. Clabaugh Trading with the Communists. Washington, D.C.: Center for Strategic Studies
1968 1969 Research analyst, House Republican Conference, headed by Melvin R. Laird
1969 Married Linda Claire Leventhal
1969 1970 Confidential assistant to the special assistant of Secretary of Defense Melvin R. Laird, Department of Defense
1970 1974 Staff member, United States Representative Philip M. Crane; chief of staff, 1970-1973; campaign manager, Crane for Congress, 1972; special assistant 1973-1974
1972 Member, Mont Pelerin Society; treasurer, 1978-1996, 1999-?; president, 1996-1998; senior vice president, 1998-2000
1973 Founder with Paul M. Weyrich, Heritage Foundation; founding trustee, 1973; member, Board of Trustees, 1974-1977, 2013-; corporate secretary, 1975-1977; executive vice president, 1977; president, 1977-2013; interim president, 2017
1973 1974 President and chief operating officer, Schuchman Foundation Center for the Public Interest
1974 1976 Member, United States delegation to the meetings of the International Monetary Fund/World Bank meetings
1974 1977 Executive director, Republican Study Committee, United States House of Representatives
1976 Published Congress and the New International Economic Order. Washington, D.C.: Heritage Foundation Editor China-The Turning Point. Washington, D.C.: Council on American Affairs
1977 1986 Incorporator with William Casey and Antony Fisher and vice chairman, International Center for Economic Policy Studies, New York, N.Y.; renamed Manhattan Institute of Policy Studies, 1981
1977 2001 Publisher, Policy Review magazine, Heritage Foundation
circa 1977 1996 Chairman, Institute for European Defence & Strategic Studies, London, England
1980 1981 Member, Executive Committee of the Presidential Transition of president-elect Ronald Reagan Chairman, Presidential Transition Task Force on Foreign Economic Assistance of president-elect Ronald Reagan
1980 ? Chairman, International Development Cooperation Agency/Overseas Private Investment Corporation Transition Team of president-elect Ronald Reagan
1981 Ph.D. in political science, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, Scotland Published Looking Back. Washington, D.C.: Heritage Foundation Editor with Hideaki Kase U.S.-Japan Mutual Security: The Next Twenty Years. Washington, D.C.: Heritage Foundation
1981 1982 Member, New Directions Advisory Committee, United States Information Agency
1981 1983 Member, President's Commission on White House Fellows
1982 Public member (ambassador), United States delegation to the United Nations Second Special Session on Disarmament, New York, N.Y.
1982 1994 Chairman, United States Advisory Commission on Public Diplomacy
circa 1982 1989 Consultant to White House Counselor Edwin Meese Member, Secretary of State's UNESCO Observation Review Panel
1983 Published Conservatives Stalk the House: The Republican Study Committee. Ottawa, Ill.: Green Hill Member, Commission on Security and Economic Assistance (Carlucci Commission on Foreign Aid)
1984 Published U.S. Foreign Policy in Asia and the Pacific. Washington, D.C.: Heritage Foundation
1985 1996 Member, National Advisory Board, Center for Education and Research in Free Enterprise, Texas Agricultural and Mechanical University, College Station, Tex.
1987 1988 Domestic policy consultant to President Ronald Reagan
1987 1999 Director, Sequoia National Bank
1988 ? Member, Sarah Scaife Foundation
1989 Awarded Presidential Citizens Medal by President Ronald Reagan Published A Foreign Policy in Service of Freedom. College Station, Tex.: Center for Education and Research in Free Enterprise, Texas Agricultural and Mechanical University
1989 1993? Member, United States Committee on Improving Effectiveness of the United Nations
1993 Published The Quiet Revolution. Washington, D.C.: Regnery Publishing
1995 1996 Vice chairman, National Commission on Economic Growth and Tax Reform (Kemp Commission)
1996 Staff director and counselor to Republican vice presidential candidate Jack Kemp
1996 2004 Member, Board of Visitors, George Mason University, Fairfax, Va.
1997 2001 Member, Congressional Policy Advisory Board
1998 Editor March of Freedom: Modern Classics in Conservative Thought. Dallas, Tex.: Spence Publishing Co.
1999 Published Intellectual Pilgrims: The Fiftieth Anniversary of the Mont Pelerin Society. Washington, D.C.: Heritage Foundation
1999 2000 Member, International Financial Institution Advisory Commission (Meltzer Commission)
2000 Editor Leadership for America: The Principles of Conservatism. Dallas, Tex.: Spence Publishing Co.
2005 Member, Gingrich-Mitchell Congressional United Nations Reform Task Force
2006 Published with Doug Wilson Getting America Right: The True Conservative Values Our Nation Needs Today. New York, N.Y.: Crown Forum
2006 Member, Honorary Board of Trustees, Fundación Burke, Madrid, Spain
2009 Recipient, Charles Heoflich Lifetime Achievement Award, Intercollegiate Studies Institute, Wilmington, Del.
2012 Recipient, Bradley Prize (Lynde and Harry Bradley Foundation) for extraordinary talent and dedication at the John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, Washington, D.C. Published with Brian Tracy The American Spirit: Celebrating the Virtues and Values that Make Us Great. Nashville, Tenn.: Thomas Nelson
2013 Resigned presidency, Heritage Foundation Recipient, Ronald Reagan Lifetime Achievement Award
2013 Chairman of the Advisory Board and Chung Ju-yung Fellow, Asian Studies Center, Heritage Foundation
2016 2017 Member, transition team of president-elect Donald Trump
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Edwin J. Feulner, Jr., (1941- ) span the years 1934-2014, with the bulk of the material dating from 1966 to 2012. The papers are organized into the following series: Personal File, Chronological File, Heritage Foundation, Organizations, Other Professional Files, Speech and Trip Files, Writings, and Digital Files. The collection documents Feulner's career devoted to conservative public policy and the rise of the Heritage Foundation as the leading conservative think tank and public policy research organization during Feulner's presidency.
The Personal File series is a compilation of material relating to Feulner's personal life and interests, his education, and other records documenting his life and accomplishments. A section of family papers includes Feulner's correspondence with his parents, siblings, children, and several uncles who were Catholic priests, with the largest portion being copies of letters and notes sent by him. A general correspondence file contains his correspondence with friends, associates, businesses, and organizations spanning over forty years. Diary entries for the years 1980-1982 offer Feulner's reflections on his work on the presidential transition team and his meetings and interactions during the early years of the Ronald Reagan administration. A grouping of appointment books and daily schedule card files is most extensive for Feulner's time at the Heritage Foundation, although there are gaps in coverage. Biographical information files and a collection of press clippings and other items mentioning Feulner help to provide an overview of his life and activities.
The Chronological File series consists of correspondence spanning the years 1965-2013 that provides an in-depth look at Feulner's personal and professional endeavors before and during his years at the Heritage Foundation. A majority of the copies of this outgoing correspondence appears on pink paper.
The Heritage Foundation series constitutes the bulk of the papers and documents the work of the this conservative public policy think tank promoting a strong national defense, tax cuts and reform, welfare reform, free trade, free enterprise, free markets, less government, and traditional values. Folders for this series are stamped with the letters THF, the abbreviation used by Heritage Foundation staff to indicate the foundation. Highlights include the Board of Trustees files, correspondence, reports, financial records, meetings, notebooks, administrative memoranda, and a people file. The Board of Trustees files provide insight into the policy- and decision-making processes of the foundation and includes budget proposals, committee meeting files, correspondence shared with the board, financial reports, and memoranda sent to the board members by Feulner. The committee meeting files are largely comprised of briefing booklets prepared for individual meetings. Feulner's memoranda to the members is a chronological file of individual memoranda that in some instances has other material attached. Correspondence shared with the board consists of letters and copies of letters that Feulner passed on to board members. Actual correspondence relating to the Board of Trustees is part of the Heritage Foundation's main correspondence file that is arranged into Board of Trustees, general, internal memoranda, members of Congress, miscellaneous, and White House. The correspondence file covers a myriad of conservative issues and policies and documents the internal workings of the Heritage Foundation. The general correspondence, arranged chronologically by year and therein alphabetically, was designated by Feulner's staff as "whites" because his replies appeared on white paper. Providing further insight into the foundation are the annual, quarterly, and weekly reports. The 2011 annual report is absent. Some of the quarterly reports are incomplete, and the weekly reports for the years 1980-1995, 2007, and 2011-2013 are absent. The financial records, consisting mostly of cash reports and monthly reports, are incomplete. The meetings file consists mostly of agendas, some with attached material or short notes penned by Feulner, for the senior management, weekly management, and other meetings of the Heritage Foundation. The weekly management meetings are often designated as MMM referring to Monday management meetings. Contained in Feulner's notebooks are further notes on these and other meetings. The administrative memoranda, miscellaneous correspondence, and miscellany were created from unfiled material found in the papers.
The Heritage Foundation's people file is comprised of correspondence, clippings, speeches, and other material concerning prominent conservatives as well as Heritage Foundation board members. It is a compilation of overlapping files originally grouped under the headings people, very important persons, and board members. Correspondents include Richard V. Allen, Belden Bell, William J. Bennett, David R. Brown, William F. Buckley, Jr., George Bush, Joseph Coors, Philip M. Crane, Shelby Collum Davis, Midge Decter, Milton Friedman, Newt Gingrich, Jack Kemp (1935-2009), Russell Kirk, Friedrich A. von Hayek, Robert Henry Krieble, Ernest W. Lefever, Lewis E. Lehrman, Donald J. Lipsett, Clare Boothe Luce, Edwin Meese, John William Middendorf, Ronald Reagan, Henry Regnery, J. Frederic Rench, Thomas Anderson Roe, Donald Rumsfeld, Thomas A. Saunders, III, Richard M. Scaife, Frank J. Shakespeare, William E. Simon (1927-2000), Margaret Thatcher, and Paul M. Weyrich. Arrangement is alphabetical by name of person and therein chronologically.
The Organizations series contains files relating to Feulner's membership in various organizations, boards, councils, commissions, and committees outside of the Heritage Foundation. Featured in this series are the Aequus Institute, Alpha Kappa Psi, Clare Boothe Luce Program of the Henry Luce Foundation, Council for National Policy, Credit International Bank and Sequoia National Bank, George Mason University, Institute for European Defence & Strategic Studies, Intercollegiate Studies Institute, National Commission on Economic Growth and Tax Reform, Philadelphia Society, Regis University, Sarah Scaife Foundation, and the United States Advisory Commission on Public Diplomacy. Included in this material are board and committee reports, memoranda, meeting documents, financial records, correspondence, legal records, and other general information regarding these organizations and Feulner's involvement in them.
The Other Professional Files series is comprised of files pertaining to Feulner's professional employment in the years prior to 1977 and assignments in later years outside of the Heritage Foundation. The earliest material pertains to Feulner's initial work relating to conservative public policy, as a public affairs fellow, first at the Center for Strategic Studies at Georgetown University and then assigned to the staff of Melvin R. Laird, head of the House Republican Conference, in the United States House of Representatives. Other sections focus on his years as legislative assistant and administrative assistant for Representative Philip M. Crane and his time as president of the Schuchman Foundation Center for the Public Interest. The largest portion of this series concerns Feulner's years as executive director of the Republican Study Committee, a conservative caucus in the United States House of Representatives, from 1974 to 1977. Included are briefing books for members, material relating to the Republican Study Committee's Campaign Fund for 1976 Congressional elections, files pertaining to policy issues, and a chronological grouping of work papers that document the work of the group. This Republican Study Committee material is closely related to documents pertaining to Feulner's doctoral dissertation and subsequent book on the Republican Study Committee located in the Writings series. Other files relating to assignments Feulner undertook during breaks from his Heritage Foundation duties cover his work on Ronald Reagan's presidential transition team and two White House consultancies during the Reagan administration as well as his work as staff director and counselor to Republican vice presidential candidate Jack Kemp during the 1996 presidential campaign. A subject file is comprised mainly of research files on issues of interest to political conservatives, that Feulner compiled during the years he was working as a public affairs fellow and in Congressional staff positions with the House Republican Conference and the Republican Task Force on East-West Trade. There are also files related to other projects and topics of interest. Individuals featured in this series include Richard V. Allen, Philip M. Crane, Jack Kemp, and Melvin R. Laird.
A Speech and Trip Files series combines several overlapping speech, trip, and event files. The series covers various speaking engagements, trips, and other activities Feulner attended as president of the Heritage Foundation and as a member of numerous other organizations. Many of the events and engagements occurred in the Washington, D.C. area, but Feulner also traveled extensively around the United States and internationally. On his international trips, he generally traveled to multiple cities and countries. Feulner's focus on Asia is recorded by his many trips to South Korea, Hong Kong (China), Taiwan, Japan, China, and Thailand. Some speeches and conference files can be found in the Organizations series.
The Writings series is comprised of articles and columns, book reviews, books, essays, manuscripts, and a dissertation written by Feulner. Topics include conservative public policy, Congress, the United Nations, China, South Korea, the Soviet Union, foreign trade, economics, national defense, and the Republican Study Committee. By far the largest amount of material consists of Feulner's research and drafts for his doctoral dissertation "Evolution of the Republican Study Committee" that evolved into his book Conservatives Stalk the House: The Republican Study Committee. Most of the research material for the dissertation and book was pulled from Feulner's files as executive director of the Republican Study Committee. The bulk of the committee's files are located in the Other Professional Files series.